<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<root><word_of_day><word>obdurate</word><meaning>hardened and unrepenting stubborn inflexible</meaning></word_of_day><thought_of_day><thought>The aim of education
should be to teach the child to think,
not what to think</thought><author>John Dewey</author></thought_of_day><categories><category>Environment</category><category>Health and Fitness</category><category>Technology</category><category>Other</category><category>Culture</category></categories><moderators><id><moderator>bobparker</moderator><link>2</link></id><id><moderator>jaskaran</moderator><link>12</link></id></moderators><capture><link>2</link></capture><editor_pick><image>2</image><link>2</link> <title>Africa: arts and cultures</title><text>
<content><div>Humans first evolved in Africa, walking upright about five million years ago, and making the first tools about two and a half million years ago using the opposable thumb. The British Mu</div></content></text></editor_pick><news><id><title>Special chance examination march 2012</title><text>PTU has declared its datesheet for special chance examination for the session march 2012. The datesheet for the same can be found on college website or on ptu website.</text></id><id><title>Best College in Placements Awards during the year 2011</title><text>It is matter of great pleasure that Guru Nanak Dev Engineering College,
 Ludhiana has been awarded Best College in Placements Awards during the
 year 2011 in appreciation of commendable contribution of the institution
 by Punjab Technical University, Jalandhar on the occasion of its 16th
 Foundation Day Celebration on 16th January, 2012.
 
 This has become possible due to rich infrastructure, faculty and best
 efforts put in by the Management as a whole and T and P Team in particular.
 
 We convey felicitations to all concerned and expect similar type of
 efforts in future also.
 
 Director</text></id></news><articles><article><image>2</image><link>2</link> <title>Africa: arts and cultures</title><text>
<content><div>Humans first evolved in Africa, walking upright about five million years ago, and making the first tools about two and a half million years ago using the opposable thumb. The British Museum collection includes objects dating from this time, but also represents historic and contemporary societies across the continent.</div><div>Long before contact with Europe, several African states, including ancient Egypt, Aksum, ancient Ghana, Mali, Songhoy, Ile Ife, and the Benin kingdom, became well known in different parts of the continent. Brass works from Ile Ife and from Benin are among the most famous objects in the Museum collection. Other states, such as the Asante Confederation, the Bakuba and Buganda developed later.</div><div>The centralised government systems of these kingdoms were based on the exclusive authority of the ruler, or king, whose power was often justified through religious ideology. They were the only ones who had the power to break social rules and to take human life and could delegate it to selected dignitaries.</div><div>If many of the kingship systems have now vanished, some have succeeded to survive in modern states, still playing important social, cultural and political functions in regions such as Asante, Benin and Bakuba. Many other African peoples live outside of centralised kingdoms. These include the Nilotic peoples of the Sudan, Kenya and Ethiopia, the Koi/San of Southern Africa and the Tuareg of the Sahara.</div><div>Contemporary art, both for the art market and for the indigenous market, thrives. Ancient skills in ceramics textiles metalwork and sculpture continue to flourish. The past century has seen the development of new art forms such as the printed cloth known as kanga in Eastern Africa, wax prints and fancy prints in Western and Central Africa. Recycling of manufactured goods â&#128;&#147; whether clothes, tyres, tins or weapons â&#128;&#147; provide an easy source of raw materials of endless variety.</div><div>Woven textiles and other fabrics are embedded in the culture of Africa. Often decorated with brilliant colours and intricate designs, they are available in almost every part of the continent. The designs and the slogans printed on them represent a subtle and complex form of communication.</div><div>The African galleries at the British Museum include objects relating to both ancient and contemporary cultures, as well as exploring contemporary issues. The Tree of Life is a powerful memorial to war, while other displays look at the subject of facing HIV/AIDS in Tanzania.</div></content></text></article><article><image>3</image><link>3</link> <title>INCAS</title><text>
<content><div>From their capital, Cuzco, in the central Peruvian Andes, the Inca created a huge empire reaching over 2,400 miles along the length of the Andes. The supreme head of state was the king, considered a living god ruling by divine right and the royal family controlled important areas of government such as the army.</div><div>The empireâ&#128;&#153;s economy was based on taxed labour. People contributed part of their labour to the state and the state-controlled religion. People farmed and herded animals, worked in mines and produced specialised goods such as clothing and pottery. The surplus was stored in numerous warehouses (tambos) for use by the army and state labourers.</div><div>Inca colonists were settled in newly conquered territories as a way of managing subject peoples and spreading Inca language and customs. Local lords were enlisted into the system of government to maintain order in their provinces, rebellious communities were resettled in the Inca heartland.</div><div>Inca engineers and labourers built a network of thousands of miles of roads and bridges to connect the empire. They constructed administrative centres, storehouses and military bases. A system of runners carrying information recorded on knotted strings called quipus also linked the capital to the regions.</div><div>The capital of Cuzco was the centre of the Inca world. Radiating from the central plaza the four main Inca roads led to the four corners of the empire. A sacred city of temples, royal palaces and residences for housing carefully-preserved bodies of dead rulers, early histories say the Inca likened Cuzco to the body of a puma (wild mountain cat), a symbol of Inca royalty.</div><div>The most sacred building in Cuzco was the Coricancha, a temple devoted to the sun, the main Inca deity. Its stone walls were covered in sheets of gold to reflect the sunâ&#128;&#153;s light.</div><div>From this temple a system of  ;sight-lines (ceques) radiated outwards dividing the surrounding landscape like slices of a pie. Over 300 shrines were situated at sacred places along these lines and there formed part of a sophisticated agricultural calendar.</div></content></text></article><article><image>4</image><link>4</link> <title>Massive Extinctions From Human Activity</title><text>
<content><div>Despite knowing about biodiversityâ&#128;&#153;s importance for a long time, human activity has been causing massive extinctions. As the Environment New Service, reported back in August 1999 (previous link): â&#128;&#156;the current extinction rate is now approaching 1,000 times the background rate and may climb to 10,000 times the background rate during the next century, if present trends continue [resulting in] a loss that would easily equal those of past extinctions.â&#128;&#157; ;</div><div>As explained in the UNâ&#128;&#153;s 3rd Global Biodiversity Outlook, the rate of biodiversity loss has not been reduced because the 5 principle pressures on biodiversity are persistent, even intensifying:</div><div>1.Habitat loss and degradation</div><div>2.Climate change</div><div>3.Excessive nutrient load and other forms of pollution</div><div>4.Over-exploitation and unsustainable use</div><div>5.Invasive alien species</div><div>Most governments report to the UN Convention on Biological Diversity that these pressures are affecting biodiversity in their country (see p. 55 of the report).</div><div>The International Union for the Conservation of Nature (IUCN) maintains the Red List to assess the conservation status of species, subspecies, varieties, and even selected subpopulations on a global scale.</div><div>Extinction risks outpace any conservation successes. Amphibians are the most at risk, while corals have had a dramatic increase in risk of extinction in recent years.</div><div>Research of long term trends in the fossil record suggests that natural speed limits constrain how quickly biodiversity can rebound after waves of extinction. Hence, the rapid extinction rates mean that it could take a long time for nature to recover.</div><div><br/></div><div>Additionally, as reported by UC Berkeley, using DNA comparisons, scientists have discovered what they have termed as an â&#128;&#156;evolutionary concept called parallelism, a situation where two organisms independently come up with the same adaptation to a particular environment.â&#128;&#157; This has an additional ramification when it comes to protecting biodiversity and endangered species. This is because in the past what we may have considered to be one species could actually be many. But, as pointed out by scientists, by putting them all in one group, it under-represents biodiversity, and these different evolutionarily species would not be getting the protection otherwise needed.</div></content></text></article></articles><most_popular><mp><link>2</link> <title>Africa: arts and cultures</title></mp><mp><link>3</link> <title>INCAS</title></mp><mp><link>4</link> <title>Massive Extinctions From Human Activity</title></mp></most_popular><archives><node><month>March</month><year>2012</year><count>3</count></node></archives></root>